[Music]
the word halitosis is derived from the
latin greek terms for abnormal or
diseased breath so it may be less of a
medical term and more of a marketing
term as it was supposedly coined by the
listerine company
halitosis is commonly referred to as bad
breath though medical and dental
professionals often use instead of bad
breath the less judgy term breath odor
as described in the journal of breath
research halitosis has been classified
into four types there's genuine
halitosis either transient or chronic
which is contrasted with pseudohalitosis
when someone thinks they have bad breath
but it's evidently all in their head and
halitophobia
where they start out with genuine
halitosis but then they treat it and get
rid of it but still think they have it
these are rare though the vast majority
of cases are ioh which stands for
intraoral halitosis bad breath arising
from inside the mouth as opposed to
lungs or stomach and not just anywhere
in the mouth but specifically in most
cases apparently coming off the coating
on the tongue
most people have a tongue coating a
grayish white deposit on the tongue
which is the main cause of bad breath
and now there are pathological
conditions like black hairy tongue whose
symptoms may include
an unattractive appearance of the tongue
which can be caused by certain drugs but
the normal tongue coating is just a thin
slightly moist whitish substance across
the upper surface of the tongue composed
of slothed tongue cells bacteria seepage
from our blood supply and secretions for
our gums and post nasal area like mucus
discharged from our sinuses dripping
onto the back of our tongue
those with gum disease tend to have four
times as much coating in terms of the
wet weight scraped off the tongue due to
the migration of white blood cells from
periodontal pus pockets onto the
tongue's surface but even in people with
perfect dental hygiene food particles
can get trapped between all the little
bumps and craps on the tongue and form a
thick bacterial biofilm coating
if we eat the right foods though our
mouth may be self-cleaning
just the act of chewing and swallowing
foods that actually mean chewing can
cleanse off the tongue leaving you with
just the normal thin layer of coating
but fast food is engineered to be eaten
fast it's soft you can just you know
gulp it down and consequently the
thickness of the tongue coating might
increase and that could contribute to
bad breath but you don't know
until you
put it to the test
the effect of a chewing intensive high
fiber diet on oral halitosis a
randomized clinical crossover study in
which subjects were examined over a
period of two and a half hours after
consumption of a high fiber versus low
fiber meal using an organoleptic
assessment of halitosis
although a few electronic bad breath
detectors have appeared on the market
organoleptic scoring is still the gold
standard
which is just a fancy name for when
dentists or doctors just give your
breath a sniff
here's the ratings they used no
halitosis detected even up close and
personal or yeah bad breath but only up
to about four inches away or out to a
foot or all the way out to more than a
yard we know halitosis is reduced by
eating due to the self-cleaning of the
mouth while chewing food and it seems
obvious that foods that need to be
chewed more intensively have a stronger
self-cleaning effect than foods that
require less chewing but whether this is
actually the case had never been
examined
until now
the participants were randomized to a
high fiber hide shoe meal with a whole
grain roll with jam and a raw apple
versus a low fiber low chew white bread
roll with jelly and a cooked apple and
the result a significantly lower bad
breath score immediately after the high
fiber meal and then two and a half hours
later compared to the low fiber meal the
researchers conclude that a chewing
intensive high fiber meal led to a
greater reduction of halitosis
[Music]
you